Guide to the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 17, The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union records, 1903-1965; 1971; 2,457 reels
  - Opis 2: Plenums of the VKP(b) Central Committee, 1918-1941, 88 reels) (Reel 2.2435-2.2457, Reel 2.2603-2.2638, Reel 2.2708-2.2736)
    - 11. Eighteenth Convocation (1939 March-1941 February)
      - Unedited verbatim record of the session of the TsK Plenum of July 29-31, 1940; verbatim records of the sessions of the said TsK Plenum re report on harvest and procurement of agricultural products and discussion of the said report, and re control over the implementation of the USSR Supreme Soviet Decree On Introduction of an Eight-Hour Working Day, Seven-Day Working Week, and of the Regulations against Employees' Resigning Voluntarily from Job at Institutions and Enterprises (G. M. Malenkov's report); verbatim record of the session of the said TsK Plenum re discussion of Malenkov's report, re establishment of the People's Commissariat of State Control, and re [election of] the commission to work out resolutions on the report about harvest and procurement of agricultural products; record of comments made at the meetings of the said TsK Plenum; stenographic report of the meeting of the said TsK Plenum re the Sovietforeign policy (not recorded), re harvest and procurement of agricultural products, re control over the implementation of the decree of the USSR Supreme Soviet on transition to an eight-hour working day, and re establishment of the People's Commissariat for State Control; protocol no. 5 of the meeting of the TsK VKP(b) Plenum of February 21, 1941, 1940 July-1941 February (Reel 2.2736, File 668-677)
      - Files 678-792 were not delivered to the Hoover Institution (Reel 2.2736, File 678-792)
  - Opis 7: Statistics Department of the TsK VKP(b), 1920-1941, 79 reels) (Reel 2.61-2.108, Reel 2.583-2.607, Reel 2.760-2.764)
    Opis 7 contains documents issued by the Statistics Department was established as a part of the TsK RKP(b) Secretariat in 1921 and was in operation until 1930. Before 1921 it was the Department of Information and Statistics and after 1930 it was the Department of Management and Instructions that dealt with statistical data. The three departments conducted statistical studies of the party composition and of its activities, and supervised registration and statistics in the local party organs. This opis includes all preserved documents of the departments for 1920-1940 (587 files on 79 reels.) Materials for 1924-1925 are not complete. The Russian finding aid to opis 7 can be found on reel 2.16.
    - Protocol of the Commission for Formatting the Survey on party activity; correspondence of the TsK VKP(b) with republican, territorial (kraevye), and provincial (gubernskie) RSDRP committees; protocols, reports and memoranda related to the financing and conducting all-party census, to issuing a unified party-membership card, to registering VKP(b) members and VKP(b) provincial organizations, to improving the work of provincial subdepartments for registration and statistics, and for safekeeping of party documents; list of party members discharged from the army, etc., 1920-1922 (Reel 2.61, File 1-23)
    - Correspondence of the TsK VKP(b) with territorial (kraevye), and provincial (gubernskie) RSDRP committees, reports, memoranda, letters, telegrams related to conducting the all-party census, to issuing a unified party-membership card, to registering VKP(b) members and VKP(b) provincial organizations, to improving statistics and registration, to publishing a book on the results of the 1922 census; protocols of conferences related to the party census and to the composition of the party and Soviet organs; lists of party officials, 1920-1923 (Reel 2.62, File 23-49)
    - Correspondence of the TsK VKP(b) with republican, provincial, and district RKP(b) committees and bureaus, and other organizations, circular letters, reports, formats for surveys related to taking all-party census, to issuing a unified party-membership card, to improving registration and statistics, registers reflecting the total number of communists in party cells (iacheiki); reports on the work of subdepartments of registration and statistics, 1920-1923 (Reel 2.63, File 50-67)
    - Correspondence of the TsK VKP(b) with republican, provincial, and district RKP(b) committees and bureaus related to taking all-party census and to processing its results, to registering VKP(b) members, to the work of subdepartments of registration and statistics under provincial RKP(b) committees, to issuing a unified party-membership card; correspondence with RSFSR plenipotentiary representatives to foreign countries, and with political administrations of the RSFSR Revolutionary Council and of the Red Army; statistical reports on the preliminary materials of the All-Russian VKP(b) census (issues 1-4); summaries of the results of the All-Russian VKP(b) census with respect to the length of party service, age, education, etc., 1920-1923 (Reel 2.64, File 68-86)
    - Statistical information and surveys presenting the results of the 1922 party census, with respect to the age, education, length of party service, occupation, social status, nationality of RKP(b) members, 1922-1923 (Reel 2.65, File 87-93)
    - Statistical surveys reflecting the results of the 1922 party census with respect to religion and desire to get education among party members, the number of members in the Communist Party of Georgia, in Moscow and in Petrograd city and provincial organizations; register of the lecturers and propagandists who are members of the RKP(b); list of party cells formed by representatives to foreign countries, 1922 (Reel 2.66, File 94-101)
    - Statistical surveys reflecting the results of the 1922 party census with respect to the membership in Petrograd city and provincial organizations, political and party work among women, party portion among industrial workers, party meetings and political campaign, social and national composition of party membership; registers of candidate members in provinces (gubernia), etc.; protocols reports, resolution pertaining to the All-Russian conference of chiefs of subdepartments of registration and statistics (uchetno-statisticsheskie) under provincial and regional (gubkom and obkom) RKP(b) committees and to the conference of chiefs of provincial and district subdepartments of information and instructions [infromatsionno-instruktorskie] under the TsK RKP(b); survey containing data about the number of people who joined RKP(b) as candidate members in July-December; report of the TsK RKP(b) Statistics Department, with information about the number of RKP(b) members, 1923, 1922-1924 (Reel 2.67, File 101-108)
    - Statistical surveys reflecting the number of RKP(b) candidate members admitted as full members, the number of party members and candidate members expelled from the RKP(b) in 1923, and the number of RKP(b) members who died in 1923, 1923 (Reel 2.68, File 109-114)
    - Information of provincial control commissions on party penalties incurred by communists; monthly reports submitted by RKP(b) provincial committees (named in alphabetical order) for January-December, 1923; summary on the activity of city, district, and provincial RKP(b) committees in provinces and republics; statements and survey about the number of communists in the rural RKP(b) cells (iacheiki); statistical surveys and reviews reflecting the total number of party members and party organizations, members of plenums and bureaus, secretaries of the provincial, regional, and district VKP(b) committees, etc.; survey of the dynamics of social composition of party organizations; letters and statements, related to the number of party members who were not registered by the 1926-1927 party census; table reflecting development of statistical documents for the 1926-1927 party census at the party organizations in military units, 1923-1929 (Reel 2.69, File 115-125)
    - Form "B" used in the 1926-1927 party census and submitted by the party organizations in military districts, 1927 (Reel 2.70, File 126-128)
    - Form "B" used in the 1926-1927 party census and submitted by the party organizations in military districts, 1927 (Reel 2.71, File 128-132)
    - Form "B" of the 1926-1927 party census taken at the party organizations army districts and fleets; registers and surveys of the number of party members and of party organizations in military detachments of the Red Army and Navy; circular and instructional letters, surveys, regulations related to the statistics departments of provincial VKP(b) committees, to local departments of registration and statistics, to a number of party members and local party organizations, to the dynamics of party social composition in 1926 and in the first quarter of 1927, to the training and further training of leading party workers, to party educational network, to the elections to the party committees and admittance to the VKP(b), 1926-1928 (Reel 2.72, File 133-143)
    - Statistical surveys, statements, registration forms, and tables pertaining to the dynamics of party social composition in 1924-1928, to the portion of communists and Komsomol (Young Communists League) members in the industrial enterprises, number of women members, admittance to and expulsion from the VKP(b), composition of provincial, territorial and republican party organizations with respect to the type of party cell composition and to the occupation, social status, and nationality of party members, to the results of women's meetings, to the party education, and to the number of party members and party organizations as of January 1, 1929; letter explaining the instruction for determining social status in numbers; draft resolution on regulating the increase in party membership, 1928-1930 (Reel 2.73, File 144-153)
    - Statistical statement on membership and social composition of the party with respect to the types of party cells; review of the information and statistics subdepartments of the TsK VLKSM (All-Union Young Communists League) Youth in Figures; preliminary plan for the VKP(b) increase in 1927-1930; quarterly surveys of the number and composition of new VKP(b) candidate members and members, and of those expelled or retired from the party, 1926-1929 (Reel 2.74, File 154-159)
    - Quarterly surveys of those expelled or retired from the party; statistical surveys, statements, and registers pertaining to the results of the party 1929 purge, to the party educational network, to the number and composition of schools, classes, and circles for political literacy, to the increase in party membership, to the portion of party and Komsomol members in industry and agriculture; memoranda and statements on regulation of increase in membership and changes in social composition of the VKP(b) and in admittance to the VKP(b); survey VKP(b) in Numbers reflecting the dynamics of VKP(b) membership, 1926-1932 (Reel 2.75, File 159-168)
    - Quarterly survey forms pertaining to the changes in distribution of party organizations among provinces, territories, and republics, and to the number of communists, 1928-1932 (Reel 2.76, File 169)
    - Quarterly survey forms pertaining to the changes in distribution of party organizations among provinces, territories, and republics, to the number of communists, and to the social composition and changes therein of city, district, and regional party organizations, 1928-1932 (Reel 2.77, File 169-170)
    - Quarterly survey forms pertaining to the social composition and changes therein of city, district, and regional party organizations, and to the number of those admitted to the VKP(b) as candidate members or made full members in 1930, 1928-1932 (Reel 2.78, File 170-171)
    - Quarterly survey forms and monthly statistical registers pertaining to the number of people admitted to the VKP(b) as candidate members and made full members in 1930, to the social composition and changes of provincial, territorial, and republican party organizations, to the number of members, social composition and changes in the Moscow city party organization; reviews and statements reflecting the increase in and composition of the VKP(b) and of delegates to regional, city, district, and provincial party conferences summoned in 1926-1927, 1928-1934 (Reel 2.79, File 171-176)
    - Quarterly survey forms pertaining to the composition and changes in the composition of city, regional, provincial, territorial, and republican party organizations; survey containing the main indexes to the VKP(b) composition before the Twelfth VKP(b) Congress, 1933-1934 (Reel 2.80, File 176-178)
    - Quarterly survey forms pertaining to the composition and changes therein of provincial, territorial, and republican party organizations; statistical reports and survey forms pertaining to the network of party organizations in provinces, territories, and republics, to the party education network, to the membership of party organizations as of January 1, 1935; table reflecting the network of party organizations in different fields of industry and agriculture as of October 1, 1934, 1934-1935 (Reel 2.81, File 178-183)
    - Survey reflecting numerical strength of party organizations with respect to their social composition and occupations of their members as of January 1, 1935; statement on the changes in party composition in 1925-1935; survey VKP(b) in Numbers reflecting the dynamics of VKP(b) membership and social composition in 1905-1935; lists of district, city, and regional VKP(b) committees reflecting the total number of citizens and of communists in a given area, and number of primary party organizations and of party members; quarterly reports on the composition and changes therein of party organizations in provinces, territories, and republics, 1935-1935 (Reel 2.82, File 184-190)
    - Quarterly reports reflecting the number of communists who were made VKP(b) members and candidate members after serving as candidate members or sympathizers; reports on the network of party organizations in provinces, territories, and republics, on the results of work in the party education network, on the number and composition of party membership with regard to propagandists in provinces, territories, and republics; tables reflecting the number of VKP(b) members and candidate members in the networks of city VKP(b) committees as of April 1, 1935, the number of party organizations in republics, territories and provinces, the number of party members in urban and rural areas, the number of women communists, and presenting comparative data on the composition of conferences of 1928/1929 and 1929/1930; statements on the number of rural party organizations, and on the network of VKP(b) organizations; survey on the membership of party organizations, of trade-unions, and on a portion of party members at big Moscow enterprises, 1929-1935 (Reel 2.83, File 191-200)
    - Materials on the registration and safekeeping of party documents in the local party organizations and changes in the VKP(b) composition; minutes of the meetings in the TsK departments, letters from the sector of party statistics to the secretaries of provincial, territorial, and other party committees related to party registration, to the replacement of workers, etc.; general surveys on membership in party organizations with respect to the social composition therein and occupations of the members; tables reflecting changes in the VKP(b) composition after the Twelfth Party Congress, changes in the numerical strength of republican, territorial and provincial VKP(b) organizations in 1929-2936; survey VKP(b) in Numbers as of July 1, 1936; lists submitted by district, city, and regional party committees with indication to the number of party cells and party members; reports on the results of party education, on the number and composition of party membership with regard to propagandists, 1934-1936 (Reel 2.74, File 201-213)
    - Reports on the results of party education, on the number and composition of party membership with regard to propagandists in provinces, territories and republics, on the network of party organizations in the republics, territories, and provinces; statements on the composition of party organizations, on the numerical strength of territorial party organizations and on changes in their network, and on the composition of rural party organizations; monthly reports on the composition and changes therein of party organizations, 1936 (Reel 2.85, File 214-221)
    - Monthly reports on the composition and changes therein of party organizations; quarterly reports on the networks and composition and changes therein of provincial, territorial, and republican party organizations; reports on the composition of and changes in party organizations of transport workers in provincial, and territorial party committees, national communist parties, etc., 1936 (Reel 2.86, File 222-227)
    - Reports on the composition and changes therein of provincial, territorial, and republican party organizations; statements about leading party cadres in 1928 and 1930, tables reflecting the numerical strength of leading cadres in MTS (Machine and Tractors Station) and collective farms, changes in the party education network and participation of communists in party studies; surveys and statements pertaining to party educational network, number of schools, classes, and circles of political literacy, number of students in Soviet and party schools, etc., in 1931-1936; card catalog reflecting numerical strength and social composition of the party (by party organizations) for 1931-1936, 1936 (Reel 2.87, File 228-232)
    - Materials related to the changes in party composition in 1933-1937; tables reflecting the numerical strength and social composition of the VKP(b) from 1924 through 1937, the increase in party members between the Fifteenth, Sixteenth, and Seventeenth party Congresses, the social composition of the party after the purge, the network of party organizations in collective farms and machine and tractor stations; lists submitted by district, city, and regional VKP(b) committees reflecting the numbers of party cells and party members; statements indicating the numerical strength of party organizations, the transfer of party members among party organizations, and admittance to the VKP(b); memoranda from the sector of party statistics concerning mistakes in the reports from local organizations; statements reflecting the number of VKP(b) members and candidate members in rural party cells for 1924 and 1925, and comparative data on the number of party cells of different type from 1922 through 1928, 1936-1937 (Reel 2.88, File 234-242)
    - Statements on the admittance to the VKP(b); monthly statistical reports on the composition of and changes in party organizations and admittance to the party, on the composition of party organs and party apparatus, on the process and results of elections to the governing party organs; lists of persons admitted to the VKP(b) in 42 organizations; statistical statements on the number of applications for admittance to the VKP(b) considered by primary party organizations; statistical reports on the composition of elected party organs and of the party apparatus in republics, territories, and provinces, on the number of officials from party apparatus who were fired from their position and expelled from the VKP(b) in the process of exchanging and examining party documents; reports on the elections to the city, regional, provincial, and territorial VKP(b) committees, to district and city party conferences, and to primary party organizations in provinces (in alphabetical order by location), 1936-1937 (Reel 2.89, File 243-252)
    - Reports (cont.) on the elections to the city, regional, provincial, and territorial VKP(b) committees, district and city party conferences, and to the primary party organizations in provinces; reports on the social composition of party organizations, on transfer and distribution of communists among organizations of different types; monthly statistical reports on the composition and changes in party organizations for January, February, and March, 1937, 1937 (Reel 2.90, File 253-257)
    - Monthly statistical reports on the composition and changes in party organizations for April, May, June, July and August, 1937, 1937 (Reel 2.91, File 258-262)
    - Monthly statistical reports on the composition and changes in party organizations for September, October, November, and December, 1937; reports on the composition of party membership with regard to the secretaries of par committees and primary party organizations as of January 1, 1937, 1937 (Reel 2.92, File 263-267)
    - Reports and memorandum on the changes in the party education network and the number of communists involved in party education; tables reflecting the composition of party membership with regard to propagandists describing the length of their service to the party, party and political education, and length of work as propagandists, numerical strength and increase in number of VLKSM (All-Union Young Communists League) members and candidate members in 1917-1935, numerical strength of VLKSM members in the Red Army, etc.; statements on the process of admitting new members to the VKP(b); memoranda and statements pertaining to the results of controlling and investigating the registration of party members and candidate members by party organizations, 1937-1939 (Reel 2.93, File 268-273)
    - Registers submitted by district and city party committees with data on the number of party cells and party members as of January 1, 1938; monthly statistical reports on the composition and changes in party organizations in January, February, March, April, and May, 1938, 1938 (Reel 2.94, File 274-279)
    - Monthly statistical reports on the composition and changes in party organizations in June, July, August, September, October, November, and December, 1938, 1938 (Reel 2.95, File 280-286)
    - Statistical reports and statements pertaining to the numerical strength and changes in military party organizations; surveys and monthly and quarterly statistical reports on the numerical strength, social composition, and changes in the party organizations in Leningrad, Moscow, and in the party organization of the political administration of Glavsevmorput' (Main Administration for Northern Way), on the social composition of the secretarial body of primary party organizations, on the party education network and composition of party membership with regard to the propagandists in the Leningrad city party organization, 1935-1939 (Reel 2.96, File 287-290)
    - Statistical summary of the admittance to the party in March-September, 1938; statistical reports on the composition of VKP(b) membership with regard to candidate members and members admitted to the party from November, 1936, through November, 1938; monthly statistical reports on the composition of party membership with regard to members and candidate members admitted to the VKP(b) in January and February, 1938, 1939 (Reel 2.97, File 291-295)
    - Monthly statistical reports on the composition of party membership with regard to members and candidate members newly admitted to the VKP(b) in March, April, May, June, and July, 1938, 1938 (Reel 2.98, File 296-300)
    - Monthly statistical reports on the composition of party membership with regard to members and candidate members newly admitted to the VKP(b) in August, September, October, November, and December, 1938, 1938 (Reel 2.99, File 301-305)